A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - General Files, Series P FA325
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Charities
  - Charities - State Charities Aid Association - Contributions, 1929-1940 (Box 17, Folder 168)
    Family contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, Homer Falks, Rockefeller Brothers Fund.
  - Charities - State Charities Aid Association - Contributions, 1942-1946 (Box 17, Folder 169)
  - Charities - State Charities Aid Association - Contributions, 1947-1961 (Box 17, Folder 170)
  - Charities - State Charities Aid Association - Westchester County Committee, 1914-1915 (Box 17, Folder 171)
    Family contributions toward cost of agency visitor to homes with adopted children. Correspondents include V. E. Macy, Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy.
    23.81
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society, 1925-1961 (Box 17, Folder 172)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. was a left member and made some contributions. Description of Legal Aid Society work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Mary French Rockefeller.
    23.9
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Westchester County, 1933-1958 (Box 17, Folder 173)
    Appeal for aid declined.
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Contributions, 1902-1925 (Box 17, Folder 174)
    Annual family contributions and gifts for special purposes. Rockefeller Brothers Fund gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Allen Wardell.
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Contributions, 1932-1948 (Box 18, Folder 175)
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Contributions, 1948-1960 (Box 18, Folder 176)
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Contributions - National Committee on Legal Aid Work, 1924-1925 (Box 18, Folder 177)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made a $5,000 contribution.
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Contributions - March 2, 1931 Pledge, 1931-1933 (Box 18, Folder 178)
  - Charities - Legal Aid Society - Contributions - June 5, 1928 Pledge, 1928-1930 (Box 18, Folder 179)
  - Charities - National Legal Aid Association, 1950-1956 (Box 18, Folder 180)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made a $50,000 contribution to the development fund, 1951. 1956 appeal was declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Arthur Jones.
    23.91
  - Charities - Travelers Aid Society, 1911-1930 (Box 18, Folder 181)
    Family contributions to the Society. Gifts through the Davison Fund, Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Report on Society's activities. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    23.10
  - Charities - Travelers Aid Society, 1931-1959 (Box 18, Folder 182)
  - Charities - Travelers Aid Society, 1931-1959 (Box 18, Folder 0182A)
  - Charities - Travelers Aid Society - Contributions, 1942-1952 (Box 18, Folder 183)
    Letters of transmittal and acknowledgement.
  - Charities - Travelers Aid Society - Contributions, 1953-1959 (Box 18, Folder 184)
  - Charities - Travelers Aid Society - Contributions, 1953-1959 (Box 18, Folder 0184A)
  - Charities - National Travelers Aid Association, 1920-1922 (Box 18, Folder 185)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions. Raymond B. Fosdick report on Association, 1922. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    23.101
  - Charities - National Travelers Aid Association, 1921-1950 (Box 19, Folder 0185A)
  - Charities - Protestant Unity League, 1923-1934 (Box 19, Folder 186)
    Served as coordinating center for Protestant work assisting needy Protestants in New York City. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed because of Mrs. Ballard's interest. There was office opposition to a centralized "Protestant" charity agency. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, E. L. Ballard.
    23.11
  - Charities - Westchester County Council of Social Agencies, 1920-1950 (Box 19, Folder 187)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave small annual contributions. Changes in organization and studies of county welfare problems. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    23.121
  - Charities - Westchester County Council of Social Agencies, 1950-1955 (Box 19, Folder 188)
    See also Box 56, Folder 625.
  - Charities - Westchester County Council of Social Agencies, 1956-1961 (Box 19, Folder 189)
  - Charities - Westchester County Council of Social Agencies, 1956-1961 (Box 19, Folder 189A)
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor, 1906-1923 (Box 19, Folder 190)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. friendship with C. N. Bliss. Office giving policy and contributions. Running of the Junior Sea Breeze summer camp. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., C. N. BLiss, Starr J. Murphy, Robert W. Bruere.
    23.13
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor, 1923-1939 (Box 19, Folder 191)
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Contributions, 1927-1939 (Box 19, Folder 192)
    By John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Contributions, 1897-1918 (Box 20, Folder 193)
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Sunset Lodge, 1925-1940 (Box 20, Folder 194)
    Contributions and description booklet.
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Ward Manor, 1929-1936 (Box 20, Folder 195)
    Endowment Pledge.
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Boys' Camp, 1923-1927 (Box 20, Folder 196)
    Contribution.
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Jefferson Needlecraft Shop, 1922-1928 (Box 20, Folder 197)
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Mulberry Health Center, 1929-1933 (Box 20, Folder 198)
    Pledge.
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Home Hospital, 1912-1918 (Box 20, Folder 199)
  - Charities - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Hospital at Sea Breeze, 1905-1915 (Box 20, Folder 200)
    Contributions.
  - Charities - Employment Bureau for the Handicapped, 1925-1927 (Box 20, Folder 201)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas B. Appleget.
    23.14
  - Charities - Goodwill Industries, 1932-1961 (Box 20, Folder 202)
    Appeals to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined. Some small gifts by Mary French Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Mary French Rockefeller.
  - Charities - Goodwill Industries, 1932-1961 (Box 20, Folder 0202A)
  - Charities - Speedwell Society, 1930-1954 (Box 20, Folder 203)
    For the care of convalescent children in foster homes. One gift by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    23.15
  - Charities - New York State Association for Crippled Children, 1949-1960 (Box 20, Folder 204)
    Small gift by Mary French Rockefeller. Other appeals were declined. Correspondents include Mary French Rockefeller.
  - Charities - New York State Association for Crippled Children, 1949-1960 (Box 20, Folder 0204A)
  - Charities - New York State Association for Crippled Children - Westchester Branch, 1954-1961 (Box 20, Folder 205)
    Appeals ignored.
  - Charities - League in Aid of Crippled Children, Inc., 1942-1959 (Box 20, Folder 206)
    Appeals ignored. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    23.16
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society, 1895-1919 (Box 20, Folder 207)
    Appeals for aid, family contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard.
    23.17
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society, 1919-1952 (Box 20, Folder 208)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society, 1943-1961 (Box 20, Folder 209)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society, 1945-1955 (Box 20, Folder 0209A)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller Correspondence, 1930-1961 (Box 20, Folder 210)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - Contributions, 1940-1952 (Box 21, Folder 211)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - Contributions, 1940-1952 (Box 21, Folder 0211A)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - Contributions, 1949-1961 (Box 21, Folder 212)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - Contributions, 1940-1961 (Box 21, Folder 212A)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - Harlem Health Center, 1929-1945 (Box 21, Folder 213)
  - Charities - Children's Aid Society - Harlem Health Center - Children's Excursion, 1927-1932 (Box 21, Folder 214)
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children, 1943-1961 (Box 21, Folder 215)
    Appeals for aid were declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    23.18
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children, 1943-1961 (Box 21, Folder 0215A)
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1945-1956 (Box 21, Folder 216)
    Association made grants to organizations working with crippled children. Laurance S. Rockefeller was Treasurer of the Association; Rockefeller offices advised on its gifts; Laurance S. Rockefeller handled the investment of its endowment funds. In 1951, Laurance S. Rockefeller resigned as the Association's Treasurer, and in 1955 he resigned his position as a member of the Council. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Alice Fitzgerald, R. B. Marston, Mary French Rockefeller.
    23.18L
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Laurance S. Rockefeller - Contributions, 1941-1952 (Box 21, Folder 217)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller's contributions.
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Belding Trust, 1945-1951 (Box 21, Folder 218)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller was responsible for the handling of the Trust. Shifting of securities, financial decisions. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, R. B. Marston.
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Bequests, 1947-1952 (Box 21, Folder 219)
    Notification to Laurance S. Rockefeller of bequests received by the Association. Legal problems. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, R. B. Marston.
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Welfare Council, 1946-1948 (Box 21, Folder 220)
    Annual contribution by Association to the New York Welfare Council. Discussion of the Council's budget. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, R. B. Marston.
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Reorganization, 1946 (Box 22, Folder 221)
    Discussion of changes in organization after Association received an endowment of $11,000,000. Suggestion made by the Rockefeller office. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, R. B. Marston.
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Reorganization, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 222)
  - Charities - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Reorganization, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 223)
  - Charities - New York Milk Committee, 1909-1919 (Box 22, Folder 224)
    Contributions were made toward supplying milk to needy children. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
  - Charities - New York Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, 1897-1911 (Box 22, Folder 225)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributions, 1894-1905. Explanation for stopping contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Starr J. Murphy.
    23.19
  - Charities - New York Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children - Heckscher Foundation, 1921-1923 (Box 22, Folder 226)
    Appeal for aid to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. No real interest shown.
  - Charities - Federation of the Handicapped, 1941-1961 (Box 22, Folder 227)
    Appeals for aid all declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
  - Charities - Federation of the Handicapped, 1950-1961 (Box 22, Folder 0227A)
  - Charities - American Federation of the Physically Handicapped, 1945-1960 (Box 22, Folder 228)
    Appeals declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
  - Charities - American Federation of the Physically Handicapped, 1950 (Box 22, Folder 0228A)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, 1925-1960 (Box 22, Folder 229)
    Rockefeller contribution. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    23.20
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 0229A)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children - Contributions, 1922-1945 (Box 22, Folder 230)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children - Contributions, 1945-1955 (Box 22, Folder 231)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children - Contributions, 1956-1960 (Box 23, Folder 232)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children - Contributions, 1960 (Box 23, Folder 0232A)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children - Mary French Rockefeller Contributions, 1939-1961 (Box 23, Folder 233)
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, 1937-1959 (Box 23, Folder 234)
    Discussions of animal control in Westchester. Contributions. Declination of all later appeals. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Hamilton P. Fish.
    23.21
  - Charities - Westchester County Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, 1937-1959 (Box 23, Folder 0234A)
  - Charities - Westchester County Recreation Commission, 1924-1951 (Box 23, Folder 235)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions toward work with the colored population. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association, 1919-1933 (Box 23, Folder 236)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions. Studies of the Association's work. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    23.211
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association, 1932-1949 (Box 23, Folder 237)
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association, 1950-1960 (Box 23, Folder 238)
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association, 1953-1960 (Box 23, Folder 0238A)
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association - Contributions, 1934-1949 (Box 23, Folder 239)
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association - Contributions, 1934, 1950-1955 (Box 23, Folder 240)
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association - Contributions, 1955-1961 (Box 24, Folder 241)
  - Charities - American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, 1931-1966 (Box 24, Folder 242)
    Most appeals declined, but one small gift from Laurance S. Rockefeller. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    23.22
  - Charities - American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, 1931-1966 (Box 24, Folder 0242A)
  - Charities - Public Health Nursing, 1920-1924 (Box 24, Folder 243)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives toward experiment in public health nursing in Westchester County. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, Beardsley Ruml.
  - Charities - New York Women's League for Animals, 1939-1961 (Box 24, Folder 244)
    Contributions by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller.
    23.23
  - Charities - New York Women's League for Animals, 1948-1961 (Box 24, Folder 0244A)
  - Charities - Little Missionary's Day Nursery, 1914-1951 (Box 24, Folder 245)
    Contributions to Christian settlement work on the Lower East Side of New York City. The Nursery operated summer camps in New York and New Jersey but its program was reduced after 1930. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    23.24
  - Charities - Little Missionary's Day Nursery - Thanksgiving and Christmas Contributions, 1919-1931 (Box 24, Folder 246)
  - Charities - Association for the Help of Retarded Children, 1951-1961 (Box 24, Folder 247)
    Appeals declined. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel.
  - Charities - Association for the Help of Retarded Children, 1951-1961 (Box 24, Folder 0247A)
  - Charities - Association for the Help of Retarded Children - Westchester Chapter, 1949-1960 (Box 24, Folder 248)
  - Charities - Association for the Help of Retarded Children - Westchester Chapter, 1949-1960 (Box 24, Folder 0248A)
  - Charities - American Women's Association, 1899-1927 (Box 24, Folder 249)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $50,000 toward building owned by American Women's Realty Corporation. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Laura Spelman Rockefeller.
    23.25
  - Charities - Infantile Paralysis, 1916-1920 (Box 24, Folder 250)
    John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions toward support of nursing care for polio victims in Westchester County and New York City. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
    23.26
  - Charities - Committee on Negro Welfare of the Welfare Council of New York City, 1942 (Box 24, Folder 251)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $2,500 for Negro work of the Welfare council in 1942. No further requests were made. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    23.32
  - Charities - Legal Size Material (Box 55, Folder 617)
    Folders 108-234.
  - Charities - Westchester County Children's Association - Legal Size Material (Box 55, Folder 618)
    Folders 237 and 239.
  - Charities - Westchester County Council of Social Agencies (Box 56, Folder 625)
    Westchester County CSA, Inc. - Cash Receipts and Disbursements of Restricted Funds, 1951.
    Removed from Box 19, Folder 188.
  - Charities - Welfare Council of New York City (Box 56, Folder 626)
    "The Burden of Wealth," 'The Saturday Evening Post,' January 5, 1929.
    Removed from Box 14, Folder 136.
  - Charities - American Law Institute - Magazine Article, 2 copies (Box 56, Folder 627)
    "Right Handling Can Reduce Youth Crime," "Life" Magazine, 1942.
    Removed from Box 11, Folder 103.
  - Charities - Magistrates' and Other Courts (Box 56, Folder 629)
    Children's Court Arraignments for Delinquency - Commitments to State Prisons and City and State Reformatories - Statistics for the Years 1929-1939.
    Removed from Box 12, Folder 112.
  - Charities - Greater New York Fund (Box 56, Folder 630)
    Resolution document acknowledging service by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in the 1950 campaign, 1950.
    Removed from Box 13, Folder 122.
  - Charities - Community Council of Greater New York, Inc. - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Award (Box 56, Folder 631)
    "Better Times," May 16, 1947.
    Removed from Box 14, Folder 140.
- Cleveland Projects
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Associated Charities, 1899-1918 (Box 24, Folder 252)
    John D. Rockefeller's annual $1,000 contribution, eventually made through the Federation for Charity and Philanthropy. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Automobile Club, 1913-1921 (Box 25, Folder 253)
    $10 annual dues, correspondence.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Automobile Club - Orphans' Outing Day, 1910-1919 (Box 25, Folder 254)
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Automobile Club - Euclid Avenue Development, 1905-1907 (Box 25, Folder 255)
  - Cleveland Projects - Children's Fresh Air Camp, 1905-1913 (Box 25, Folder 256)
    John D. Rockefeller made small annual contributions. He also gave $5,000 in 1903 and $1,000 in 1912. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Community Fund, 1927-1940 (Box 25, Folder 257)
    John D. Rockefeller gave $30,000 in 1930 and 1931. Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial contributed from 1919 to 1928. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt.
  - Cleveland Projects - Euclid Avenue Association, 1922-1941 (Box 25, Folder 258)
    Association to promote equitable taxation and harmonious city planning. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. became a member because of a housing venture and paid dues regularly but did not actively participate. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Federation for Charity and Philanthropy, 1904-1918 (Box 25, Folder 259)
    Federation organized to systematize giving. John D. Rockefeller gave through the Federation to charities which he had been supporting. Annual contributions were between $9 and $10,000. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Federated Churches, 1912-1931 (Box 25, Folder 260)
    Small annual contributions by John D. Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
  - Cleveland Projects - Floating Bethel, 1899-1926 (Box 25, Folder 261)
    Missionary work for Great Lakes sailors. Also, a home for friendless children. Small annual donations made because of Jones, who directed Bethel. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., J. D. Jones.
  - Cleveland Projects - Fourth of July Celebration, 1910-1913 (Box 25, Folder 262)
    John D. Rockefeller contributions toward "safe and sane" Fourth. $50 annual contribution. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller.
  - Cleveland Projects - Hiram House, 1900-1915 (Box 25, Folder 263)
    John D. Rockefeller gave small annual gifts to this settlement house. He gave $10,000 to the building fund and $17,500 for additions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller.
  - Cleveland Projects - History of Cleveland, by W. G. Rose, 1948-1950 (Box 25, Folder 264)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. underwrote two hundred copies of the book. Authorized distribution was done by the publisher. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Home for Aged Colored People, 1904-1914 (Box 25, Folder 265)
    Small annual gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Humane Society, 1899-1920 (Box 25, Folder 266)
    Society worked to prevent cruelty to animals and small children. $100 gifts were given for many years. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Cleveland Projects - Children's Industrial School and Home, 1898-1905 (Box 25, Folder 267)
    John D. Rockefeller gave annual contributions.
  - Cleveland Projects - Children's Industrial School and Home, 1905-1913 (Box 25, Folder 268)
  - Cleveland Projects - Jones School and Home for Friendless Children, 1903-1914 (Box 26, Folder 269)
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Medical Library, 1903-1906 (Box 26, Folder 270)
    John D. Rockefeller gave a contribution to the building fund. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller.
  - Cleveland Projects - Cleveland Orchestra Concerts, 1886-1949 (Box 26, Folder 271)